[Waco] First Baptist Church records, Inclusive: 1892-1978, Bulk: 1940-1947
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
[Waco] First Baptist Church records
Inclusive: 1892-1978, Bulk: 1940-1947
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
119
[Waco] First Baptist Church
4 document boxes.
The [[Waco] First Baptist Church records consists of correspondence, literary documents, and financial records that pertain to or are associated with the First Baptist Church of Waco.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
The First Baptist Church of Waco was established on 1851 May 31 by four charter members along with Noah T. Byars, who became their first pastor on June 1. Originally the church met in the meeting place of the First Methodist Church. In 1857 the congregation moved to a building located at Fourth and Mary until 1877 when the building was destroyed by a fire. Construction for a new building began immediately. The new structure was completed in 1883 and lasted until 1907. The current building was erected in 1907 located on Fifth and Webster.
In the early 1870’s under the direction of Rev. B.H. Carroll the church underwent innovative changes such as the introduction of instrumental music in worship. During this time period First Baptist Church of Waco also allowed Women to serve as deacons. They also were invited for the first time, by Rev. B.H.Carroll, to the Southern Baptist Convention in 1883.
In 1915, First Baptist Church’s longest serving pastor, Dr. J.M. Dawson, started his tenure. Dr. J.M. Dawson concentration was on the church budget. During his tenure a campaign was launched called Southern Baptist Convention’s 75 Million Dollar Campaign. The First Baptist Church was assigned with raising 200,000 dollars, the largest portion given to any church. Even during the Great Depression Dr. J.M. Dawson was still dedicated to the church budget even sacrificing his own salary. Dr.J. M. Dawson was also concerned with social issues such as racial and gender prejudice and the separation of church and state. Along with his pastoral duties he also served vice president of the Baptist General Convention of Texas in 1922, the chairman of the Southern Baptist Committee on World Peace in 1945, and the chairman of the Executive Committee of the Southern Baptist Convention from 1945 to 1946. He also served on the board of trustee for various institutions such as Baylor University and the Southern Baptist Convention. J.M. Dawson also published twelve books including his autobiography, and was the editor of the Western Evangel in 1906 and the Baptist Standard from 1943 to 1946. The First Baptist Church of Waco is credited for establishing the Waco Classical School, that later became Waco University. This University would merge with Baylor University in 1886 .The First Baptist Church also has been involved in the creation of two seminaries. One was the Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary located in Fort Worth and also the George W. Truett seminary located on Baylor University campus. Along with universities First Baptist Church also contributed to the founding of Hillcrest Baptist Medical Center in 1919.
Baylor University and First Baptist Church have retained a strong relationship since 1886. Many of Baylor’s Presidents, administration, staff and students are members of the First Baptist Church. The First Baptist Church is also known for its college ministry such as the former Fidelis and Baraca Groups, and providing opportunities for service. To this day First Baptist Church of Waco is still active and serving the Waco community.
Scope and Content
The [Waco] First Baptist Church records contain correspondence, literary documents, and financial records about the operations of the First Baptist Church of Waco. Notable records include information about the Baraca group, a Bible study group for college-age women, and their outreach to female students at nearby Baylor University. There are a variety of manuals, essays, reports, yearbooks, budgets, and other administrative information, as well as outreach and Sunday worship service materials
Arrangement
Originally the [Waco] First Baptist Church records had an inventory for one box but the collection did not have a finding aid.
Currently the [Waco] First Baptist Church records are organized into six series: I. Young People’s Department, II.Fidelis and Baraca Groups, III. Church Events, IV. Literary Religious
Documents, V. Budget Announcements and Meetings and VI. Organ Committee.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 119. Acquired 0-00-00
Related Resources
Related collection materials
The Benajah Harvey Carroll Papers also contain documents about the First Baptist Church of Waco.
Related references
Lefever, Alan J. "First Baptist Church, Waco." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2012 November 11.
“Our History.” First Baptist Church of Waco. Accessed April 23, 2020.
Reynolds, J. A. "Dawson, Joseph Martin." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed November 29, 2012.
Texas Historical Commission. “First Baptist Church of Waco.” Historical Marker. Accessed 2012 November 11.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
First Baptist Church (Waco, Tex.)--History
Subjects
Baptists -- Texas -- History.; Baptists -- Texas -- Waco -- History.
Genres
Budgets.; Correspondence.; Essays.; Programs.; Publications (documents).
- Young People's Department, 1940-1949, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  This series consists of service programs from the Young People's Department. This series also consists of literary documents such as publications that pertain to the Young People’s Department.This series is in average condition.
  - Young People's Department Literary and Correspondence: General, 1940,1945,1947,1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Young People's Department Programs (1 of 6), 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Young People's Department Programs (2 of 6), 1945 January-August (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Young People's Department Programs (3 of 6), 1945 September-December (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Young People's Department Programs (4 of 6), 1946 January-March (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Young People's Department Programs (5 of 6), 1946 April- July (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Young People's Department Programs (6 of 6), 1946 September- December,1947 January- February (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Fidelis and Baraca Groups, 1932-1947, undated; 2
  This series consists of correspondence, Sunday programs and advertisements pertaining to the Fidelis and Baraca Groups. These two groups were bible classes for college students; the Fidelis for the girls and the Baraca for the boys. This series also consists of letters the group would send to new Baylor female students to convince them to join Fidelis. This series is in good to average condition.
  - Fidelis Group: Literary (1 of 3), undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Fidelis Group: Literary (2 of 3), undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fidelis Group: Literary (3 of 3), 1937,1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - My Dear Baylor Girl Letters, 1932-1940, 1947, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Baraca Group: General, 1938-1939, 1944, 1947, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Fidelis and Baraca Groups: General, 1938-1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Church Events, 1892-1958, undated; 3
  General condition: Good.
  This series consists of literary productions and correspondence pertaining to church events including Sunday service programs and church events scheduled during the week. This series is in good condition.
  - Sunday Services (1 of 4), 1892, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sunday Services (2 of 4), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sunday Services (3 of 4), 1936-1946 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Sunday Services (4 of 4), undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Holiday Services (1 of 2), 1934-1942 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Holiday Services (2 of 2), 1943-1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Additional Programs, 1927, 1934, 1936-1938, 1940-1943, 1946-1947, 1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - The Evangel Publication (1of 2), 1927 1932 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - The Evangel Publication (2 of 2), 1935-1937, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Sunday School Documents: Convention, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Sunday School Documents: Programs, 1945 June 24-1945 August 19 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Sunday School Documents: General, 1936, 1939-1940, 1946-1947, 1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Invitations and Promotional Documents (1 of 9), 1927, 1932-1935,1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Invitations and Promotional Documents (2 of 9), 1939-1944 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Invitations and Promotional Documents (3 of 9), 1945-1957 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Invitations and Promotional Documents (4 of 9), undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Invitations and Promotional Documents (5 of 9), undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Invitations and Promotional Documents (6 of 9), undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Invitations and Promotional Documents (7 of 9), undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Invitations and Promotional Documents (8 of 9), undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Invitations and Promotional Documents (9 of 9), undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Baylor University and First Baptist Church Events and Promotional Documents (1 of 4), 1926, 1932, 1934,1936 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Baylor University and First Baptist Church Events and Promotional Documents (2 of 4), 1940-1947 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Baylor University and First Baptist Church Events and Promotional Documents (3 of 4), undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Baylor University and First Baptist Church Events and Promotional Documents (4 of 4), undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Literary Religious Documents, 1892-1978, undated; 4
  This series consists of documents such as poems, religious publications involving religious matters or that mention the First Baptist Church. This series features a number of yearbooks from various church groups such as the Women’s Auxiliary Group, Women’s Mission Union, and Timothy Eunice Lois Sunday School.This series includes various forms of Church letterhead. This series is in good condition.
  - “Why This Building” by Charles C. Carroll, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - “Why This Building” by Charles C. Carroll Handwritten draft, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - “The Issue Before Us: Its Threat To Religious Liberty” by Harold E. Lindsey, 1960 July 27 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - “The Issue Before Us: Its Threat To Religious Liberty” by Harold E. Lindsey Second Stage Draft, 1960 October 16 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - “The Issue Before Us: Its Threat To Religious Liberty” by Harold E. Lindsey Final Draft, 1960 October 16 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Beneath Two Stars, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - “Sketches of First Baptist Church” by Judge W. H. Jenkins, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Treasure Thoughts of Our Friends Books, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - New Year Report, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Poems and Songs, 1937, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Manual of the First Baptist Church, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Women’s Auxirliry Yearbook, 1927, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Women’s Missionary Union Yearbook (1 of 4), 1938, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Women’s Missionary Union Yearbook (2 of 4), 1942, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Women’s Missionary Union Yearbook (3 of 4), 1943-1944, 1950-1954 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Women’s Missionary Union Yearbook (4 of 4), 1953-1956 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - First Baptist Church Yearbook, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Literary Items for Mother’s Day, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Mother’s Council Yearbook, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Timothy Eunice Lois Sunday School Class Yearbook, 1930, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Church Clubs’ Documents and Correspondence Lists (1 of 6), 1934, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Church Clubs’ Documents and Correspondence Lists (2 of 6), 1945-1947 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Church Clubs’ Documents and Correspondence Lists (3 of 6), 1947 July, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Church Clubs’ Documents and Correspondence Lists (4 of 6), undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Church Clubs’ Documents and Correspondence Lists (5 of 6), undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Church Clubs’ Documents and Correspondence Lists (6 of 6), undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Promotional Documents, 1949-1958 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Church Forms (1 of 4), 1933 September 13, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Church Forms (2 of 4), undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Church Forms (3 of 4), undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Church Forms (4 of 4), undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Church Stationary, 1934, 1938, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Budget Announcements and Meetings, 1925-1957, undated; 5
  This series consists of budget reports and promotional items to increase the church budget. This series consists of an account book from 1943. This series is in average condition.
  - Offering Envelopes, 1936, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Budget Lists (1 of 7), 1925-1927 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Budget Lists (2 of 7), 1930-1935 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Budget Lists (3 of 7), 1936 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Budget Lists (4 of 7), 1937 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Budget Lists (5 of 7), 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Budget Lists (6 of 7), 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Budget Lists (7 of 7), 1942-1947,1957 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Budget Forms and Stewardship Cards (1 of 2), 1936, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Budget Forms and Stewardship Cards (2 of 2), undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Budget Announcements: General, 1934 March 22 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - The Account Book of FBC, Waco (1 of 10), 1942-1945 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - The Account Book of FBC, Waco (2of 10), 1943 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - The Account Book of FBC, Waco (3 of 10), 1943 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - The Account Book of FBC, Waco (4 of 10), 1943 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - The Account Book of FBC, Waco (5 of 10), 1943 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - The Account Book of FBC, Waco (6 of 10), 1943 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - The Account Book of FBC, Waco (7of 10), 1943 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - The Account Book of FBC, Waco (8 of 10), 1943 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - The Account Book of FBC, Waco (9 of 10), 1943 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - The Account Book of FBC, Waco (10 of 10), 1943 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Organ Committee, 1911-1918, undated; 6
  This series consist of documents pertaining to First Baptist Church acquiring a new organ. This series includes letters and brochures from various organ manufacturers around the country. This series includes telegram correspondence and a sketch of the church organ. This series is in good condition.
  - Correspondence (1 of 7), 1916 November (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence (2 of 7), 1917 April-May (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence (3 of 7), 1917 June 1-11 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence (4 of 7), 1917 June 13 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence (5 of 7), 1917 July 9-21 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence (6 of 7), 1917 July 26 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence (7 of 7), 1917 August 1 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Telegrams (1 of 2), 1917 June 9-12 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Telegrams (2 of 2), 1917 July 13- August 10 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Notes, 1915, 1918, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Organ Manufacturers (1 of 8), 1916 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Organ Manufacturers (2 of 8), 1916, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Organ Manufacturers (3 of 8), undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Organ Manufacturers (4 of 8), undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Organ Manufacturers (5 of 8), undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Organ Manufacturers (6 of 8), 1915 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Organ Manufacturers (7 of 8), 1916 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Organ Manufacturers (8 of 8), 1911, 1917, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)